I always promote insurance a lot in my videos and personally
So after listening to me, one of my friend had taken health
insurance of his entire family
So one day when his father was coming home from office
He met with an accident
After which he was taken to the hospital
Where his treatment was going on for 5 days
And in his treatment, a total of 3 lakh rupees were spent
Now because he had taken health insurance of 6 lakh rupees
So his entire bill should have been claimed from the
insurance
But there is a twist here
And that twist is that the health insurance he had taken
He took it through an agent So he didn't know that in his
health insurance 1% per day room rent is the limit
Means 1% of 6 lakh is 6000
So he could only get 6000 rupees per day of room
Whereas in the hospital where he had admitted his father
There his room rent was 12000 rupees per day Now you will
say that it's okay He will have to pay the remaining 6000
per day from his pocket
Means 30,000 for 5 days
So the remaining 27,000 will be paid by the insurance
company
But there is one more twist here
And that is because 6000
Your room rent 12,000 is 50% of it
So in this situation, your total cover will also be
calculated as 50%
Means instead of 3 lakh, he got 1.5 lakh rupees
So this is what happens when you get your health insurance
through an agent without any knowledge
So see, the way I will tell you in this video
In that, in comparison to the agent You will get health
insurance for 10-20% cheaper But wherever you take health
insurance from Make sure that The health insurance that you
are taking There should not be any room rent limit And in
case you have taken
a health insurance
Which has a room rent limit
Then you can add a feature like No Room Rent to that health
insurance Due to which you will never face any problem due
to room rent cap
Now the second most basic mistake people make while taking
health insurance
That is how much cover amount they should take health
insurance
They do not decide this properly
But before telling you about the cover amount
In this video, I will show you by buying health insurance
live
So you will be able to buy your health insurance by yourself
And you will also understand
What you have to see before buying health insurance
So before taking health insurance
Generally people make mistakes
And their claim never gets passed
First we will discuss about that
And after that we will buy health insurance live
So watch the video till the end
So see how hospital expenses are increasing today
Even in small diseases 2-3 lakhs of expenses can be easily
done
And if there is a little big disease
Then there can be expenses of 15-20 lakhs easily in the
hospital
Means your whole life's earnings can go to the hospital
So it is necessary to take a reasonable amount of health
insurance
And how much should be that reasonable amount according to
you
Let's calculate it So the formula to calculate it is Your
annual income plus
In the last 5 years
The expense in the hospital is 50% So according to you
The right cover amount will be 10 lakhs
Which is your annual income
And the 5 lakhs that you have spent in the last 5 years
That is 50% Means 2.5 lakhs So 10 lakhs plus 2.5 lakhs
means 12.5 lakhs
Now in case
If you have not spent anything in the last 5 years
Then the amount of your annual income
Health insurance should be taken at least
And if your annual income is very less
Let's say 3 lakhs or 4 lakhs
Then also you should take health insurance of minimum 5
lakhs
Because no disease will come by looking at your salary
Now the next mistake
Because of which 90% people do not take health insurance
That is
They think they already have health insurance
Which their company is providing them
So if you are also
So if you are also not taking health insurance
Thinking that our company is providing
Then what is the need
So in such a situation
If you want to understand that you have a good health
insurance
Or you just feel that there is health insurance
So to find out
Now first of all
The formula I told you
Apply that formula
How much health insurance you should take
And how much you have received
Generally companies
Give health insurance between 2 to 5 lakhs
Which will not fulfill your basic requirement
And in that also
There is a room rent limit
And along with that
The biggest problem here is
Whenever you change your company
Then your health insurance ends
And in case there is a recession
Because of which someone's job goes
So along with the loss of the job
That health insurance will also go
So the company that is providing you health insurance
Don't sit on its trust
Get your personal health insurance
Now let's talk about CSR
Claim Settlement Ratio Now you will say that I know this
And I have taken my health insurance after seeing it
Or if I will take it, I will take it after seeing it
But you know that
Companies also know this
That's why they always try
That their claim settlement ratio is good That's why the
company never completely
Rejects the claim It will reject half of your claim Due to
which their claim settlement ratio will be good
And new people will keep taking insurance
So the claim settlement ratio
Tells us how many claims the company has
And how many claims it has passed So this should be more
But along with this
You should also look at the company's Incurred Claim Ratio
The formula for the Incurred Claim Ratio is
Total value of claim settled by an insurer
Divided by the total value of premium Collected by the
insurance company
And if we multiply this by 100 Then it comes out in
percentage terms Now if a company's
ICR is less than 50%
Then we can understand that the company
Is collecting a lot of premium
But is not settling the claims accordingly
So this is very good
According to the insurance company's business
Because the company is profiting a lot
But when you are getting insurance from that company
Then this is a negative sign for us
Because the company knows
That people look at the claim settlement ratio
That's why the company easily passes
The small claims
And the big claims
Sometimes the company delays in passing the big claims
Or rejects them
Or partially passes them
So that the claim settlement ratio is correct
Let's understand this with an example
Suppose a company has 99 claims worth 1 lakh
And one claim is worth 1 crore
So the company will pass 99 claims worth 1 lakh
But the claim worth 1 crore
Which is a big claim
Will either delay in passing
Or may be reject it
So in this case
The claim settlement ratio will be 99%
So you can buy insurance from that company
But if you look at the amount
Then the company has passed
Less than half of the claims
So before buying insurance
Check the company's ICR
Which is 60-70%
Then you can consider it
So let's learn how to buy health insurance
To buy health insurance
I am using policybazaar
Let me clear that
We have a material connection with policybazaar
But I genuinely believe
That it is best to buy health insurance from policybazaar
So the link to buy health insurance From policybazaar is
given in the description Now as soon as you click on that
link
You will be redirected to this page Now here you can see
That if you buy online insurance
Then you can get a discount of up to 25%
So for whom do you want to buy insurance
You have to select here
Like I want to buy for myself So I have clicked on self
If you are married
So you can select your wife
If you want to buy for your son
If you want to buy for your daughter
If you want to buy for your father
If you want to buy for your mother
You can select all of them from here
Right now I want to buy for myself
So I have clicked on self
Now after clicking on this
You have to click on continue
After clicking on continue
Here you have to select your age So here I have selected my
age After selecting age
Now you have to enter your city
So I live in Dehradun
So I have selected my city
Now here it is asking your medical history
So if you have any of these diseases
Then you can select it
So I don't have any disease
So I have selected none of the above
Now after coming here
You can see many insurance plans
But before going to these insurance plans
You should first apply some filters
So that the insurance plans that come in front of you
Those qualities are already there
So here you can see the option of all filter
You can click on it
Now after clicking on it
You can see the option of cover So you have to select how
much cover you want
So most people take cover of 10 to 24 lakhs
So I have selected it
Now after this next option is coming Room rent type So I
told you that you should generally
Buy such insurance In which there is no room rent limit
So we have selected it
Now after this, let's talk about policy benefit
So select three things in it
Which is pre-hospitalization
Post-hospitalization and day care treatments
In pre-hospitalization
Suppose if there is any expense
Which is happening before being admitted in the hospital
So that will be covered
In post-hospitalization, all those expenses will also be
covered
Which are after being treated from the hospital
And along with that
In day care treatments, those treatments will also be
covered
Which happens within a day
Because health insurance generally works
Only when you are being admitted in the hospital
So there is no need to select this
When plans come in front of you You can select there
After this, there is an option of existing disease waiting
period
So generally there are some diseases
Which may happen to you already
Like suppose if there is a kidney stone
Then it will not happen suddenly
So in this case, there is a waiting period of insurance
Which is often very long
So if you want
That the period should not be more than a year
Then you can select it
For now, I let it be no preference
So if you want to see the plans of some top companies
Then you can see that too
Before starting the video, let's understand the details of
the plan.
This was the plan at the top, so I am selecting it.
As soon as I selected it, I can see 24 cashless hospitals
here.
And these are shown according to Dehradun.
In whichever city you are in, according to you, another
plan can be better.
So here you have to see the plan in which there are maximum
cashless hospitals.
So in this, 24 cashless hospitals can be seen.
Now I see some other plan in which we will also see how
many cashless hospitals are there.
So here we are getting to see 33 cashless hospitals.
After this, let's see some other plan.
So in this plan, we are getting to see 41 cashless
hospitals.
But before buying, it is also very important to see some
more coverage.
And do not miss this at all.
See very carefully what I am going to tell you.
So here you have seen the features.
According to you, where there are more cashless hospitals,
it is better.
So there are more cashless hospitals in this.
So now let's talk about the features.
So first of all, it has passed 99.4% claims in the last 3
months, which is a good thing.
Secondly, I told you that there should be no room rent
limit.
So here you can see any category.
That is, there is no room rent limit.
After this, let's move forward.
So here cashless hospitals are more than 11,000 in the
whole of India.
But here is another very important thing.
And that is co-pay.
This co-pay is the most important thing.
Because even in this, you may have to pay from your pocket
many times.
So there are many such insurance policies in which it is
possible that there is a 5% co-pay.
So in this case, if your bill comes to Rs. 10 lakh, then
its 5%, i.e. Rs. 50,000, you will have to pay from your
pocket.
But see when you are taking health insurance, then why do
you have to worry so much?
So always see that whatever health insurance you are
buying, there is 0% co-pay in it.
And here you can see that there is 0% co-pay.
That is, the whole money will be given by the insurance
company.
Apart from this, it also covers 90 days of
pre-hospitalization and 180 days of post-hospitalization.
Which is sufficient.
Apart from this, you can see what additional features are
available in your plan.
And here is a very important option of waiting period.
Do see that too.
Which is 4 years for existing illness.
You can reduce it a little through riders.
And here is the initial waiting period of 30 days.
So in this way, whatever details I have told you about
health insurance, after checking all of them, if you feel
that you should buy that health insurance, then you have to
click on proceed to buy.
So after seeing all these features, if you feel that you
should buy this health insurance, then you have to click on
proceed to buy.
After that, this window will open in front of you.
So here you can see that your cover amount is Rs. 10 lakh.
Plus Rs. 10 lakh extra from the first day.
After this, if we talk about riders, then you don't have to
buy too many riders.
But if you want to reduce your pre-existing waiting period
from 4 years to 1 year, then you can select this rider here.
So as soon as you add it, you will see that your total
premium amount has increased.
So because right now I am making this video just to teach
you, that's why I remove this rider.
Now after this, if you feel that the amount is too much and
you want some discount, then if you are ready to buy a
shared room, then you can apply here on the shared room,
which will save you Rs.
So you can see that my total premium has decreased here.
So I remove it again.
After this, you can see a lot of add-ons here.
You can read about the policy that you will buy.
And if you feel it is necessary, then you can add it.
But for now, I click on Proceed to Proposal.
So after this, you have to click on Escape and Continue
here.
Now as soon as we click on it, it is asking for our details
So I have given my name, along with my marital status.
Gender, pen card name, means whatever basic details are
there, you have to fill here.
So after filling all these details, you have to click on
Proceed to Medical Questions.
After this, you will be asked some medical questions here.
If you have any of these diseases, then select it after
selecting Yes here.
I don't have any disease, so I am selecting No.
After this, some more questions are being asked here.
So you have to answer them correctly.
Don't give any wrong answer intentionally.
Because this can cause you problems in claiming.
After this, you have to click on Continue to Nominee
section.
So here you have to enter the details of your nominee.
So I am entering the details of my father, so I have
written his name here.
After filling all these details, you have to sign some
declarations here.
So to sign them, click on Continue.
Now here you will get an option to check your details.
And here you can see how much time you want to pay.
For example, if you pay for 3 years, then you can save Rs.
2200 here.
And for 3 years, you will get this insurance for only Rs.
19,875.
Right now, I am making this video just to show you.
That's why I am paying for 1 year.
So here we have to select 1 year and click on Proceed to
Payment.
Now when we click on Proceed to Payment, we get a lot of
payment options here.
Here I am selecting the option UPI.
And after that, we get a QR code here.
So now I will scan this QR code and make the payment.
So here it comes in front of us.
And I am going to make the payment.
You can see.
You can see that it has been updated here too.
And this is our payment.
Now after the payment, it will ask for an OTP verification
from you.
So that OTP will come to your mobile number.
The mobile number that you have entered.
So here my OTP has come.
So I will enter that OTP.
So after entering the OTP, we have to click on Verify.
After that, here you have the option to confirm your
address.
So you have to click on Use this address.
And after doing all this, your policy will be issued within
24 hours.
Along with this, you will also get a dedicated relationship
manager here.
With whom you can contact when you have to claim the policy.
Or if there is any confusion.
So in this way, you can buy your health insurance at home.
And you can compare and see.
When you buy your health insurance online.
So here you will get to see that insurance is cheap.
And along with that, whenever you need to claim insurance
here.
You have two options.
One is you can contact the company directly.
Or if you want, you can also contact the policy market.
And the policy market also helps you to claim your
insurance.
So the link of the policy market is given in the
description.
From there you can buy your health insurance.
So do check the description.
I hope you liked the video.
If you liked the video, then do like it.
To watch more videos like this, do subscribe to the channel.
And if you have seen the video so far, then you are very
special for us.
Do tell by commenting.
Thank you!